welcome good morning morning about half
the people here have their eyes
open
uh Gina you ready
5.21 yeah there we go uh I had one more
question about this thing by uh Master
vasu Okay Abid
mosha and the uh the Tibetan goes
it means you have in the Abid Dharma you
have 46 mental functions going on in
your mind two of them are causing you
trouble and that's why they don't say
body and mind usually they say uh what
do they
say five five piles of stuff five piles
of stuff
and by the way that's exactly what the
translation is five piles of stuff okay
you could say five heaps but it's like
just five piles of random stuff okay
uh and we were saying that in in
especially narina but also all of
Buddhism uh they don't say uh you are
your body and your mind and then you is
just named on your body and mind they
don't say that they say you are named on
your five parts your five piles of stuff
okay and then we were kind of asking why
why don't you just say body and mind and
they say because the mind should be
always
divided uh and there's two
troublemakers out of the 46 and they are
discrimination yeah affing and
discrimination so my you know my
question to you which I always wondered
about uh it says uh
in the Sanskrit it says in the tietan
it's and it
means they are the causes of sansara
okay they cause all your
trouble we uh in
order one by one okay it says
K it means in order what's it
mean anybody have a guess I just want to
guess raise your hand eat your
box no there's two two mental functions
okay which are feeling and
discrimination
somehow they cause
trouble one after the other which what's
your theory my theory is that feelings
cause you to
discriminate so why one is related to
the other I think that's pretty good she
said I I think feelings cause you to
discriminate this person makes me feel
good this person doesn't make me feel
good therefore I like this person and I
don't like therefore this person is
different from the other person right is
that I think that's pretty good I think
that's pretty
good that's a cheap answer all
right okay good
answer so
before you get enlightened you have a
body and a
mind uh you have your five piles of
stuff and then after you get enlightened
do you still have your five piles of
stuff
yes yes but they're
purified he said yes but they're
purified okay and and what's the
investigation we're in chapter
22 which
investigation
those who G yeah tagata those who have
gone that way uh what's what's their
nature okay we're we're inside of that
investigation and
specifically how do you change when you
go from one to the other okay do you
have a body and a mind before you get
enlightened do you have a body and a
mind after you get enlightened you know
what
changes it's just how you put them
together right it's just how you put
them together it's just how you see them
you see what I mean your seeds change
you don't change how's
that okay your seeds change you don't
change okay you don't change into
something else your seeds change okay
you're the same thing that's what the
guardian is trying to say in this
chapter that's just about all he's
trying to say okay next inum yay a i SI
I as as
what's that artificial stupid
program next picture you
guys
yeah I said give me a dog a puppy dog
with two pens in his mouth
and there's 20 other ones I don't want
to show you but this one was okay okay
and the idea is that uh before you
became a Buddha
your nature was the same you were
still uh putting a name on Two Pieces
okay you were still putting a name on
Two Pieces but it was person who's going
to die the name was person who's going
to die the pieces were body and mind or
you can say the five piles of stuff okay
but uh you were before that before you
became a
Buddha you were still just pieces say
with a name on it okay and uh after you
became Buddha you are still still pieces
with a name on it okay that's all that's
all all right you can't go to not from
not Buddha to
Buddha if the name is coming from the
pieces you can't go from not Buddha to
pie
okay if these pieces are Michael from
their side I can't become a Buddha if
these pieces are
Michael from my side then if I change my
my seeds I can I can become a budha okay
got it if these pieces were
Michael from their own side then Michael
has to die Michael cannot become a
Buddha if these pieces are Michael from
Michael's side from my seeds then I can
become a Buddha okay and and that's why
it's possible to become a Buddha okay
you created your non- Buddha and you
will create your Buddha okay but if it's
not that way there's no reason you would
change okay all right if it's coming
this way you you're kind of stuck with
it all right so thean is
saying because you are empty There's
Hope okay because you are empty there's
hope all right you can become anything
right it just depends on your seat okay
cool why did Grandpa put two pens in the
dog's
mouth
huh kind
of no no purified World unpurified I'll
say that yeah um Michael not Buddha and
Michael Buddha okay they're the same
they're just a pen okay got it Michael
before he became a Buddha and Michael
after he became a Buddha is a pen all
right same thing so put two pens in the
dog's mouth all right you know how long
it took me to get the AI to do
that all right sometimes it's kind of
stupid all
right all right let's go
next and by the way it's not supposed to
be complicated it's supposed to be
hopeful
okay if if you're coming from your
seeds then there's hope if you're coming
from your own side there's no hope okay
you can't change it okay if somehow it's
coming from you then there's hope if you
just change the seed then there's hope
if there's if it's coming from this way
there's no hope
okay my brother killed himself when he
was 20 and he was smart and he was
handsome and he was strong and he was a
almost professional Surfer in Hawaii he
went out when the Hawaiians wouldn't go
out took me with him and uh and he he
just he said this doesn't make any sense
he just he just killed himself you know
he said this is all doesn't make any
sense he said this is hopeless you know
so I think if if if it's coming from you
sorry if it's coming from its own side
it's hopeless uh and and maybe he wasn't
crazy you know if he if he believed that
but it's coming from you okay it's
coming therefore therefore you have a
chance okay all
[Music]
right I'm gonna pull you out a verse
from nag which confirms that last idea
and it's the 16th verse in this chapter
Which chapter 22 how many chapters total
are they real chapters not really
they're just a bunch of
poems okay like it's not like uh 50
pages or something like that it's like
20 poems is one chap supposedly be a
chapter what's what are the chapters
name investigation yeah an investigation
okay checking something out all right uh
next yeah uh whatever the nature of the
one gone of one gone thus is the nature
of all these beings is the very same
okay that's the two pens in the puppy's
mouth okay the the Buddhist
nature is not different from our nature
the the nature of a person who's not a
Buddha and the nature of a person who is
a Buddha neist says whatever is the
nature of the Buddha the nature of
everybody else is also the same okay
what does that mean we are not
suffering it doesn't mean that it just
means
what yeah we are pen we are pen Buddha
is a pen and we're a pen so the guard
says from one in one way the nature of
the Buddha and the nature of us is the
same okay why because we're coming from
we're coming from the seeds we are also
coming from seeds Buddha's coming from
their seeds and we are coming from our
seeds on in one way we we equal to
Buddha okay does that mean we're not
suffering
no okay got it okay that's Nea then he
says actually those who have gone that
way have no nature at all and because we
are equal to them those who are Buddhist
have no nature at
all and since we are equal to them we
don't have any nature okay first he says
whatever is the nature of Buddha your
nature is the same oh but by the way
they don't have any nature so neither do
you okay got it I'll say it again
whatever is the nature of a Buddha your
nature is the same if you're not a
Buddha okay then he says oh but by the
way you don't have any they don't have
any nature anyway so if your nature is
the same as their nature you don't have
any
nature okay got it what's it mean they
don't have any
nature from their own side that's all
from their own side are you equal to a
Buddha you are yeah you're coming from
seeds they're coming from seeds there's
nothing about them that's coming from
their side okay what about the
parts same yeah and and that divides the
highest highest
Buddhist in the in the highest
school there's two parts okay some of
them say the raw data okay the the top
and the bottom of the pen
your body and mind or
your five piles of stuff okay the lower
middleway school says they come from
their own
side okay the the raw data the pieces of
you come from their own side how you
interpret them is up to you okay got it
that's lower school lower highest
school and the highest high school says
by the way
the pieces are also coming from you you
take the side of the top you take the
left side of the top and you take the
right side of the top and you put them
together and you call it top then you
take top and bottom and you put them
together and you call it pin so it just
like that endlessly you take pieces and
and you call them something
okay okay
comfortable but there's a point at which
if you get down to the atoms of the top
you cannot see them so how do you do it
then I'll say I'll say it like this okay
what is the pen the pen is the top and
the bottom who put them together you did
you call it a pen okay where' the top
come from well you can say left side of
the top and right side of top there's a
little handle here okay the side with
the handle and the side that has no
handle and then my mind puts them
together and gives them a name when I
give them a name by the way name name
name name name name in Buddhism is a
picture coming out of your karmic seats
name is just a picture okay name name is
not a word name is a picture okay you
got to remember that when they say
Buddhism says everything is name only it
doesn't mean uh oh that's that's Teddy
that's rob it doesn't mean that it means
pictures coming out of your mind
pictures are called names in Buddhism
okay or names are called pictures how's
that okay say
again yeah you can say label yeah yeah
when you say the world is names
only what you mean is it's pictures
coming out of my seats it doesn't mean
words okay because everybody has
different words for Stuff chashka cup
caou you know everybody has different
names okay it's not the names it's the
pictures pictures okay pictures are
names in the beginning there was the
word okay some wise man
said that's the first word of the
Bible okay yeah in the beginning there
was the word okay means a picture
everything came from a picture okay so
he says uh oh so my question to you
was
okay is is the pen a
picture well it's the result of a
picture I I have a top and a bottom and
then a Karma opens in my mind a seed
opens in my mind and a picture comes out
of my mind and it unites the top and the
bottom it puts them together and and
that picture is called pen okay you can
say name the picture is the name okay
it's p it's not the sounds how many
clicks do your teeth
make you know it's not the sounds it's
the pictures so there's pictures coming
on your mind and and you see the left
side you see the top and the bottom and
then your mind puts them together into
pin okay and the dog takes the same top
and bottom and puts the them into CH
Choy okay but the pen the the the black
part and the white part are still there
okay the The Dog's Mind organizes them
in a different way because the dog has
different seeds okay got
it say
[Music]
again I'm sorry thank you the pictures
the picture can be imprint or not is
this imprint uh when you say
imprint uh that's how the seed is
planted in your mind okay it's pressed
into your mind and it give you a picture
and uh when this when you like when
you teddy needs a pen and you only have
one pen left and he says can I have your
pen and you're
like and then you give him the pen when
you let go of the pen that imprints on
your own mind that imprints on your own
mind then it cook cook cook cooks and
then a picture comes out then you have
many many pen pictures come out if you
give Teddy one pen you will have 20 pin
okay that's how I make
money no that's why I have
$100 thank you for your secret no I mean
you didn't wonder why grandpa has $100
to give out I I when I left here I was
broke I I had $30,000 debt and when I
left Retreat I was $30,000 in debt and
uh I started using seeds and uh then you
it works okay okay now where was
I uh picture picture yeah so the dog has
differences and the pictures come out of
the dog's mind and those pictures come
out on the pieces and they join the
pieces together the picture joins the
pieces together and the dog says M CH
okay they say this piece and what I'm
saying is
that for the dog to join the top and the
bottom
together they have to see the top and
the
bottom okay so is the is the top also
glued together by
picturing yeah yeah the dog takes this
side and the dog takes this side and
puts them by the way you cannot see the
whole top it's not
possible okay it's red on this
side okay really I have special pen
top it's totally red on this side okay
but you can't see it okay you can only
see part of it okay every time you put a
name on the pieces of
something you actually cannot see all
the pieces okay when you look at this
side you can't see this side if I
say if I say look at the side that has
the clip on it and you look at at your
left side right and then I'll say show
look at the side that doesn't have the
clip on it then your mind goes
you start looking at that
side there's a famous story of a a
student the teacher said you want an
apple and they said yeah you know and
they pick an apple and it's very
beautiful on this side and on this side
it's rotten you know and they say you
want an apple and this like yeah and
then they give the apple and they
go because your mind creates the whole
Apple you can't see the back of the
Apple you don't know if this is red in
the back or not okay you never see the
whole thing and you're always looking at
a piece of the thing got it yeah now I
have a question for you how about the
clip how do you see the
clip yeah the same the clip has a left
side and the clip has a right side so
now you're not looking at this part
you're just looking at this part okay
and you're looking at the left side and
right side now here's my
question what happens when you get down
so far you are looking at less than one
atom you're pretty close to having a
[Music]
perception how do you how do you see the
smallest
thing if you can't see the pieces of the
smallest you have
friends I'm going in the
monastery uh the monks when they're like
15 they get a
nickname you know like
imprint and the rest of your
life D they won't call you by your name
they say hey hey
imprint I have a friend whose name is
Momo
okay so what about when you get down to
she said bi logic right I think that's
okay yeah you think there must be
smaller pieces even though you can't see
them so you see them with your logic
how's that and then you glue those
together okay why are they talking about
all this they're trying he's trying to
say if you were not empty you could not
become a Buddha and that's the name we
are investigating what Buddhas this
whole chapter is an investigation of
Buddhas if you are not of production of
the pictures coming out of your seeds
you cannot become a Buddha if the pen is
not correct you cannot become a Buddha
that's the guardian is saying okay got
it before you became a Buddha and after
you became a Buddha you were the same
you were you were still just your pieces
okay and that's lucky so before you
became a Buddha the nature you had
before you became a Buddha and the
nature of you had after you became a
Buddha was the same what was it you had
no
nature I'll say it again the nature you
had before you became a Buddha and the
nature you have after you become a
Buddha is the same what's that nature
you don't have any
nature got it that's this verse that's
this verse okay it's not by the way when
he says you don't have a nature he means
you don't have a nature from your own
side that's all you do have a nature
that's the Budd that is the Buddha
nature exactly yeah the fact that you
don't have a nature is your Buddha
nature yeah we all
have yeah in fact they don't call it
they don't call it Buddha nature they
call it a very interesting
name to tet the GMA what's
GMA the womb the womb every human being
male or female has an extra
womb and it's your Buddha womb cool okay
everybody has it everybody has a Buddha
womb and it's what Jose said it's the
fact that you have no nature that's your
Buddha
womb if you had a nature you wouldn't
have room to become a Buddha if I have a
Buddha nature why do I don't have a
Buddha seeds
same thing well seed
are yeah that's very true yeah I went
from the beginning so I don't want
struggle and look yeah Buddha nature is
not a Buddha seed Buddha seed is a
changing thing and Buddha nature is an
unchanging thing seeds are seeds are the
most changing thing in the universe
because if they don't change they never
open right okay seeds are the most
changing thing in the universe
because if they don't change they never
open the tree never comes out of the
seed if they don't change okay but your
Buddha nature is the fact that you come
from
seeds and that never changes you you
will always have that nature before you
become a Buddha and after you become a
Buddha you will always be the result of
your sins you will always not be the
result of anything else how's that yeah
it's a negative all right your Buddha
nature is a negative you you are not you
are not not like the pen you are not not
like the pen okay that's your Buddha n
okay are you not like the pen no I am
like the pen so the fact that you are
not not like the pen not not that's your
Buddha nature
okay
yes I also have a question yeah
he's used to it she's using the uh
different difference between quality and
characteristic so she's saying that is a
true that the quality that I have before
becoming a Buddha is eus and the
character characteristic I have after
becoming Buddha is Buddha nature you can
say that although you also have Buddha
nature before that right yeah but it's
good that's a good question generally
yes uh you
have uh the quality here is
emptiness and you have that quality is
characteristic
okay difficult difficult
question okay it's a good question
that's the main question all right let's
go to the next you
know by the way I'm not teaching you the
whole book it would take about 50 years
or so uh so I'm I'm going to the most
important points and I'm choosing the
points that help you with your medicine
Buddha practice okay I'm choosing the
parts from the Gina which will help you
have a nice medicine Buddha practice
okay and and that's what we're doing I'm
not teaching you the whole book I'm
translating sona's explanation of the
whole book it took
me so far six years and I'm about one
quarter through okay it's it would take
a long time okay all right uh the next
chapter which
number 23 is an investigation of
Claus okay you can say
error uh but really it's clous claa is
the Sanskrit
word uh you can say mental Affliction I
don't like that translation because I
don't like a
translation that the English Speer
speaker doesn't know what you
mean because that's not translation so
we don't use the word Affliction in in
America in normal language I call it
waiter and waitress language you know if
you go to a peach tree Cafe and you say
could I have an
Affliction and then they say
huh if the waiter says huh then it's not
a good English translation you see what
I mean so I was there when they invented
mental Affliction I didn't like it
nobody listened to
me but no nobody uses that word in in
English Okay I mean you can find it in
some old book but nobody uses that word
so I i' like to call it a negative
emotion okay that's simple right do you
have negative emotions yeah a big bag I
am a big bag of negative emotions okay
then uh and it we it's hard to get used
to using that word if you did mental
Affliction for 20 years uh but anyway
think about it
CLA is the the
definition is
a definition of a negative emotion is it
messes up the Peace of the mind I'm
sorry it messes up the Peace of Mind of
the person who has
it that's the definition of a negative
emotion it messes up their Peace of Mind
of the person who has it okay the
definition of a negative emotion is a is
any kind of emotion which destroys the
piece of Mind of the person who's having
the negative emotion okay so it's
specific to the person who's having it
okay the the rude definition of a
negative emotion is it makes you unhappy
happy okay you can say that okay the
definition of a mental Affliction is
that any emotion which makes you
personally unhappy is is a mental
Affliction okay got
it uh sing SBA
means it's
a a piece of the mind and it's not the
main mind okay it's not General
awareness it's a flavor of the mind it's
a flavor of the Mind
and it must involve the movement of the
Mind thought has to be going on anytime
you have a negative emotion that emotion
is moving it's getting stronger it's
getting less it's aimed at one person
you decide to aim it at
everybody like that it's always changing
okay that's the definition of a one more
point and then I'll do a question
um almost every Sanskrit word
has a cognate cognate means it's an
English word which came from the
Sanskrit because all almost all English
words come from Sanskrit uh English
comes from mainly
German uh mainly Germanic languages
Germanic languages come from Latin uh
Latin comes from Greek Greek comes from
Sanskrit so so all almost all of English
comes from Sanskrit if you know how to
look you can always find an an English
word that's came from the same root so
the root is
klish uh klish and it means to disturb
your peace of mind klish the the root of
the word CLA is kich and there's only
one cognate that I'm aware of and that's
Holly okay there's a plant called Holly
and the leaves have prickles on them you
you can't touch the leaves the leaves
are very prickly they little needles on
them if you try to touch
Holly and it's funny because uh in uh
the Christmas tradition in in the
west uh if you put a holly Branch
hanging then you're supposed to kiss the
person who walks under it you know this
custom if you're in America for mistl
toone same it's the same
plant uh you're supposed to hang the
leaves in the from the roof and if you
have somebody you want them to be your
boyfriend or your girlfriend if they
walk under it you're allowed to kiss
them on Christmas Even they don't want
to
okay so why they use a prickly leaf for
this unwanted kiss I don't know uh okay
but that H comes from the same
root you know sharp sharp and prickly it
means when you have a claure in your
mind it's uncomfortable it feels
uncomfortable how do you know that
you're having a mental Affliction it's
uncomfortable it feels uncomfortable
that's the sign okay
question Yesa what is the definition of
the Peace of Mind of seeds of Peace of
Mind seeds no peace peace
peace of mind yes uh depends on if
you're talking
about uh are you talking about a lack of
distraction or are you talking about a
lack of claas you see what I mean
there's two kinds of Peace of Mind in
Buddhism one is uninterrupted
Focus uh which is called sham and Sham
means peace you want to go
deeper uh sham comes from an older
root
kasham okay like K means patience for
example shamata means peace right
krisham means uh patience okay when you
have a
ksh in
Sanskrit it often
becomes in Western
languages becomes Kava and kava becomes
q k
ksh becomes kve becomes
Q that's the strange strange English
thing q and u you know q and u came from
K and V and that came from ksh so the
word quiet comes from
shamata cool because it used to to be K
and then it changed to kav and then it
became Ka and then it became quiet cool
and calm comes from the same root okay
it used to be Kabam calm so calm and
quiet these all come from the word sha
shamata okay so the reason I brought it
up is when you say peace mental peace
there's two kinds in Buddhism one is a
lack of
distraction you know are you able to
keep your mind on your meditation object
or are you thinking about
lunch okay unless lunch is your
meditation object which is mik me and
Rob right uh so that's one kind of piece
but a a deeper kind of piece is a lack
of mental afflictions a lack of cles
okay freedom from cles no more mental
disturbances right okay to two kinds of
piece are are samcara and glaa
synonymous
uh is a sanskara means uh fresh Karma
okay karmic seed sansara means fresh
karmic seed it's the which Link in The
Wheel of Life number two link number two
okay and is it the same as
what claa yeah no because you can have
lots of virtuous Suns scars yeah
yeah but I
would there's a question of whether all
claas are
suncar I think you could say that you
think
s all negative states of Mind are are
seeds mental
seeds are fresh Karma all all negative
states of Mind anytime your mind is made
unhappy by a CLA in your mind is that a
bad is that a is that a
Karma I'd say it's probably is but the
fascinating thing if you talk this again
is uh the first
Ling uh misunderstanding which triggers
all sun
sarus is is it bad karma or Good Karma
neutral it's
neutral and that's a mystery uh I think
so gang might have figured it
out okay
but say
again you you mean all all cles are
basas or all CL are not all not only s
but also because they are R seeds
oh that's a big debate I would say
that's a big debate not will every
karmic seed
ripen will every karmic seed come close
closer to
ripening that's a big debate
yeah yeah
okay is is misunderstanding the pen a
bad
karma that's a delicate question okay uh
we can't we're going next to the 23rd
chapter the investigation of negative
states of mind okay Nega negative
emotions we're going to investigate
negative
emotions Grandpa's going to try to tie
it to medicine
Buddha because I would rather teach
medicine Buddha that way I don't want to
go through medicine Buddha Sutra and
tell you this Buddhist green and this
Buddhist blue and it's kind of boring
for me okay as far as I'm concerned it
can be any color you
want I mean it's not that important to
me but I'm curious about who they are
and how you get to be like that so uh
that's where we're going okay so
investigation of the next chapter is the
investigation of negative states of
mind question why do you think he wrote
chapter 23 after chapter
22 why why does narina have
ADD no or is there
in English we have an expression is
there a method to his Madness you know
he's looks like he's acting strange is
there a reason or is he just
strange is that there must be a
reason huh anybody is that like an
obstacle that we need to purify to
become a Buddha I like it yeah something
like that if you want to be a Buddha
you're going to have to get over these
negative emotions so let's study
negative emotions next okay
I I'll go for that I think that's a good
way to
go do all people who have removed their
negative emotions reach
buddhahood no and that's the
Nirvana uh Nirvana is the definition I
mean the the the definition of nirvana
is what's the
Tibetan
huh
yeah anyway stopping your your mental
your negative
emotions is
that yeah okay
uh so here's his first question okay and
it's
uh here's the picture how can you say
that I'm the same as a Buddha you know I
can't even stop fighting with my wife or
my husband you know and it my kids are
the witness right
uh like how Nar how can you say I'm the
same as a Buddha if I can't control
myself in the kitchen you know how can
you say I'm a Buddha like somebody's
asking him it doesn't make sense okay
you said I'm the same as the Buddha you
said my nature and the Buddhist nature
is the same but this morning I got I've
set up my wife and my husband how can I
what do you mean I'm the same as a
Buddha okay all right that's that's
where we're headed all right and here's
the root
[Music]
text
okay that's the Sanskrit the Sanskrit
sounds a lot cooler than the English
okay it's very magical okay these things
depend on a in a mistaken way on what
looks nice and what does not but those
are nothing of a nature of their own
thus then our negativities have nothing
right about them okay uh so he's he's
investigating negative states of mind
okay and here's here the ne the
investigation is starting here okay and
he says those things depend on a
mistaken way on what looks nice and what
does not
so what he's going to say in this
chapter is negative emotions are based
on feeling good about some things and
not feeling good about other things okay
then a lot of people misunderstood that
and they said I shouldn't feel good
about anything you know and then there's
whole schools of Buddhism for hundreds
of years you know never eat chocolate
you know never watch
Netflix uh never never feel good uh
that's all bad any time you feel good
it's a bad thing okay and then there's
whole hundreds of years of poor guys
sitting in a little house with no
chocolate and no necklace and then they
didn't get in line you know and they're
like what happened you know so just to
remove things that you enjoy is not
Buddhism okay it's not Budd I don't
know it's not Buddhism you you see these
uh paintings of paradise they got
parasols and flowers and Lotus Gardens
and you know I'm sure they have
Netflix and chocolate you know stuff
like that I mean it's ridiculous to say
that Buddhism means you shouldn't enjoy
anything
so that when you succeed you can go
where you can enjoy something it doesn't
make sense okay I'll say it
again Buddhist practice means never
enjoy yourself why should I practice
that so you can go to a place where you
can enjoy
yourself called toua you know the heaven
of
enjoyment it doesn't make sense you know
it just weird okay so it's not Buddhism
to it's not Buddhism to say I can't have
chocolate because it's nice you know
it's not Buddhism to say uh when you're
tired and you deserve it you can't watch
the king's
affection Korean pop what you call it K
drama K drama K-pop it's like BTS
micum
okay excellent
show okay it doesn't mean if you worked
all day trying to raise money for ACI
right
him so that you could pay your
stuff and and then you can't rest or you
can't watch a movie to to relax you know
come on that's not Buddhism okay like
Buddhists are not supposed to be serious
all the time or there's something wrong
with you you know okay anybody who
Smiles is not a
Buddhist all right it doesn't make sense
I know but you feel guilty when you
watching Netflix right you're like I'm
not a good Buddhist you know it's okay
if you watch it all day that's a problem
okay if you watch it when you're tired
and and you spend all day helping other
people that's fine you know because
tomorrow you'll be even better helping
people you'll be fresh okay all right
these things depend in a mistaken way so
some things look nice and some things
don't look nice am I supposed to
pretend is that the root of my claes is
that the root of my negativity should I
stop trying to look at nice things and
should I try to look at some not nice
things also should I watch Disney
Channel with
Netflix to make sure I get a good
balance you see what I mean like that
okay you know am I a bad Buddhist if I
don't look at some boring stuff also am
I being a
discrimination do I have discrimination
if I refuse to watch HBO but I only want
to watch Netflix is that the root of my
sansara you know am I discriminate you
know it says here uh what looks nice and
what doesn't look nice he's somehow
saying that claas are triggered negative
states of Mind negative emotions Naran
says are somehow triggered by what seems
nice to you and what doesn't seem nice
to you somehow this is triggering your
negative emotions okay got
it is it or isn't
it should you learn to watch a a real
boring movie and enjoy
it
right is that what the guardian is thing
we have to investigate it
okay uh but those are nothing of a
nature of their own uh what you find to
be a boring movie and what you find to
be an interesting movie is not coming
from the movie side okay every movie you
ever watched you wrote
it okay you can't judge your own State
of Mind by counting the percentage of
good movies and bad movies in your life
that's a direct sign of your mental
state okay I'll say it again you wrote
all the bad movies you ever saw and you
wrote all the good movies you ever saw
and the next page of an of a book when
you turn the page it's coming from you
okay when you turn the page of a novel
and does the character kiss the girl or
not if he doesn't it's your
fault okay because when you turn the
page the letters come out of your mind
okay the words come out of your mind you
can't criticize any author especially
GUI Michaels
talks uh you cannot say it was boring
gisha or didn't make sense or you know I
can't believe you didn't remember the
definition of nirvana okay
uh
anyway it's coming from you that when
you become a regular teacher every day
you could tell your students you know if
you don't like my talk just remember
it's coming from
you if you do like my talk that part's
coming from
me okay all right so uh Denny says uh
yeah your negativities are also not
coming from their own side they're also
coming from from you okay uh when you
feel off balance in a lot of
CLA the study of claas the investigation
of Claus negative states of mind uh
which is what we're doing now we're just
we're trying to figure out why do you
have a bad
mood why do you feel upset why do you
feel angry why do you have doubts you
know what seeds create
those okay that would be nice seeds to
learn to stop them
right it's a lot easier if you're a
gardener which I'm not but my wife
forces me to help her uh if you're a
gardener it's a lot easier to take
the there's a weed called Johnson grass
okay it a little piece grows up and 90%
grows
down and so it goes like 3 meters four
meters deep
and then it branches off this way and it
spreads everywhere you know
and what's really fun is if you see a
Johnson grass seed you pick it up and
you throw it in the garbage you know
send it to somebody else's
house okay all right no I mean get the
seed out of the yarn okay don't don't
dig uh don't dig Johnson grass roots for
six hours
okay just pick up the SC and throw it
out okay and then then your your life is
smooth okay so I says here uh understand
that your negative emotions are also
coming from you
okay they're also coming from your seats
don't
struggle don't struggle with your
negative emotions after they have
already gotten strong don't try to dig
out the roots after the tree is huge
okay just pick up this seed and throw it
on okay lot easier life is a lot easier
dealing with mental
Affliction seeds is a hell of a lot
easier than dealing with anger or Pride
or desire after it's beat okay it's too
it's it's it's impossible okay deal with
the seeds and don't see deal with the
emotions get rid of the seeds and then
you won't have them okay dealing with
anger after after you're angry is pretty
impossible okay dealing with jealousy
after you're jealous is impossible take
care of it before that take care of it
while it's still a seed okay that's what
he's saying okay all right next piece
let me see
here I I have a thing about bus
shelters when you say taking Refuge I
always think about bus
shelters uh so for 19 years in my
corporate life in New York City
Manhattan the the commute was two hours
in and two hours out they offered me a
helicopter uh and they offered me a
limousine and I was like this Buddhist
you know I said I'll take the bus you
know I'll take the public bus so for 19
years I took the bus and uh the way to
get the bus is you go out out and stand
under a shelter in my neighborhood cuz
CU I lived in a very poor neighborhood
Mongolian neighborhood immigrants
refugees they had no money at all
nothing and uh by the way they're coming
to
visit uh in a couple of days they're
already on the road in their car I just
found out yesterday uh my student from
50 years ago is
coming uh he was a a six-year-old kid
and now he's a famous rock
star
and I must have rubbed off on him
or uh so he's coming and and I asked him
will he play some music for us and uh so
they're coming to celebrate their
father's
Memorial uh during the fire offering so
son if you don't mind is she
here uh okay it's always good to
volunteer people who are not
here we got to set up instruments and he
agreed to play he he's bringing his
unfortunately s him he's bringing his
bass
player uh and I think his drummer and
his singer so so anyway he said his
father used to really enjoy their musing
so I said that would be a nice offering
for you father so we're gonna
dedicate the fire offering to his father
and we're gonna dedicate the rock and
roll to his father
Unfortunately they only know 60s rock
and
[Applause]
roll Grateful Dead
yeah so anyway I must have good karma
all right
uh so anyway uh when you talk about
taking Refuge it means a lot to me
because I that by the way they didn't
build the shelter for 10 years and when
it rained or snowed I was standing out
there sometimes it took a half an hour
one hour for the bus to come and so it
means a lot to me the the the shelter
the bus shelter represents taking Refuge
why is there a big birthday gift there
by the way my AI did pretty good on this
one
huh yeah in the medicine Buddha practice
by the great fifth daring
Lama uh we are starting again the seven
steps okay we are starting again the
seven steps we did seven steps in
general to all Buddhists at the
beginning now we're about halfway
through and we're going to do the seven
steps again to get ready for
negotiations with the medicine Buddha
gang
okay
like first we have to butter them up
with the seven preliminaries you know
here's the offerings here's my
confession Etc okay and then you say are
you going to keep your prayers or not
each one of you made prayers some did
four some five some 10 you know are you
going to keep those prayers or not I'm
here to I'm here to find out are you
going to keep your word or not you know
first you have to butter them up you
know here's offerings and and okay and
then then there's going to come the
moment of truth and we're going
to practice it together we're going to
practice it together and we're going to
go through some of the more to me the
prayers which are
more which are more powerful for the
world today okay like with the situation
going on in Israel or the situation
going on in Ukraine you know I I think
we should focus on the medicine Buddha
prayers which might help that situation
okay so we're going to work on those
prayers uh to start with that you have
to do your seven preliminaries again
okay so that's where we are in the sadna
when you do the sadna they're going to
ask you to do the seven steps again so
that that's Parts there the seven
preliminaries you're going to do them
again but this time it's not for all the
Buddhist in the universe it's for the
eight medicine Buddhist okay the the
gang medicine Buddha gang okay because
it's the start of a
negotiation you know you gonna keep your
word or not you know you talked big way
back when you know I got eight prayers I
got four prayers you know
well in English you say put up or shut
up like let's let's see okay let's see
if you can help us or not okay but first
you have to make them happy and that's
what we do Timothy I'm supposed to do
Q&A at 7 or what yeah correct okay in
five minutes we'll do
Q&A if in five
minutes if there's no Q there's no
a okay and I'll just I'll just go have
another coffee okay all right it
happened once I think all right okay so
we're taking shelter uh here's what it
looks like in the s t next picture you
guys
yeah and it's the same formula okay the
same formula I bow down to the one gone
thus to the defeater of the enemy to the
totally enlightened Buddha to the king
of glory whose name is proclaimed to the
corners of the universe along with his
inestimable circle of attendance
hundreds of thousands of Millions
hundreds of thousands of millions of
Bill
billion of bodh saus I make offering to
you I go for shelter to you that's the
bus shelter and the gifts the birthday
gifts right and we're gonna say that to
the first Buddhist name is good
name okay and then we got juel Moon
finest gold Beyond sandness Ocean song
sea dancer medicine Buddha somebody told
me I left out one of them in the last
list sorry about that
okay so that's the beginning okay uh I
make offering to you I go for shelter
definition of taking
Refuge
uh putting your ultimate hopes in
another
person basically it's the definition of
taking Refuge okay it has a definition
it's in Tim's text
okay symbol it means uh put your hopes
in them okay so during these prayers
we'll take the medicine Buddha Buddhas
one by one and we'll ask them for help
okay I don't know why you would think of
Buddha would help you even if you don't
ask but
somehow maybe they have a
non-interference agreement or something
if you don't ask they they don't have I
don't know okay but generally you have
to ask okay don't be shy to ask them if
they don't exist you just wasted a few
minutes if they do exist you're G to get
some help but if you don't ask they
might not help okay all right so it's
good to ask in my opinion is better to
ask okay even if you're not sure
now I told you my AI artificial
intelligence it's really stupid and uh
I've Sage's been trying trying for
months to find me a better one and he
says guess I think you got the best one
and
uh sometimes he does the right thing and
I said I want to see a picture if I
invite all the medicine Buddhist to
dinner at my
house what will it look
like
amazing
yeah hagy was it hagy he's like is there
any meat
there that I can't control at least they
didn't put wine
bottles but it's not bad right yeah
anyway
uh invite them for dinner okay that's uh
first you uh first you make offerings to
them okay and we're going to talk about
the offerings we're going to talk about
the emptiness of the offerings we're
going to say what see what neag has to
say about making offerings to Buddhas
okay Buddhas can see everything in the
universe they can be in every French
restaurant in the universe at the same
time you know why do they need your
offering okay what's the point of it you
know what's the emptiness of making
offerings to a person who can sit in
every French restaurant at the same time
okay what's the point of it how does it
work okay tune in next
class okay and that's where we're going
okay how do you serve
dinner to a person who's already at
every dinner there
is and what's the point okay cool all
right question and answer if you have if
you don't have I will take a nap right
here I have the microphone I'm sorry I'm
taking
control we're going to take a couple
questions from our online audience as we
have about five or 600 people listening
and they have pressing questions as
well um the first question gue Michael
is thank you for these extraordinary
teachings I'm wondering if it's possible
for you to explain to us how do we
Planet Jump during our meditation how do
you sorry Planet
Jump when you talk about jump jump from
planet to planet oh planet
yes um how can we do this how can we
practice doing this before seeing
emptiness directly yeah okay
good
uh there's a debate in the ancient texts
about uh first of all about whether it's
possible
to see emptiness without being a bodh
saer and it's a it's a fierce debate and
it's gone on for
centuries and Jetson capa's position is
that you can you don't have to be a bodh
SAA to see emptiness directly you know
and I I think you can think of
certain phys
physicists uh you know who have deep
insights into reality in to uh what do
you call
that
uh quantum physics I think quantum
physics is flirting with emptiness and
uh especially what's the guy's name the
position of the Observer determines the
event what's his
name what's his name Max plank no there
was another one
Heisenberg uh anyway the position of the
Observer changes the event you know WEA
um whether a proton moving through a
defraction grading acts like a particle
or a wave depends on the position of the
Observer okay and uh so I think a a a
person with deep on you know deep
scientific State of Mind could see
emptiness so I so jeton compa position
is that you don't have to be a body suff
to see to see emptiness directly that's
his
position um but
uh if you have certain seeds that this
person mentioned if you already have
those seeds in your mind and then you
see emptiness directly uh it's very
typical to become a Buddhist on the same
day uh to have this experience of
meeting every living being directly and
promising to take care of them uh that
typically happens on the same day
because chronically speaking your
central channel is open for the first
time in controlled
circumstances it's open during death
during the death process it's open
during orgasm and but it's those are
neither controlled things and to to do
it under controlled circumstances during
the direct perception emptiness while
your central channel is open you can
have the experience of of a bodh
becoming a bodh Safa okay so I would say
uh the
karma and the pronic energy to see
emptiness directly often leads to the
experience of being a bod becoming a
bodh SAA at the same time what are the
seeds that might make the difference
right the scientist sits down and has a
deep insight into reality but they could
care less about people they blew up the
first nuclear bomb not too far from my
house okay if you go west from my house
so East you hit um New Mexico and this
is where they blew up the first Adam
Bomb and they had oppenheim out there
and all this dud dudes from Princeton
and uh and and some general turns to
Oppenheimer he says is there a chance
that this could ignite the whole
atmosphere of Earth burn us all up and
he said yes there's a chance we're not
sure what's going to happen but let's
see it's so interesting you know and
that's a real scientist you know the non
bodh sappa scientist they blew up the
first nuclear bomb partly because they
wanted to see if their equations were
correct and and they took the risk that
they could stop all life on Earth
forever uh to see if their equations
were correct you know who's gonna see
they're correct I don't
know
but but that's a scientist okay and then
uh a a person who has the right seeds
when that Prana of seeing emptiness
directly moves into their Central
Channel it also causes them to have the
experience of jumping from planet to
planet meeting every living being and
promising to take care of them okay now
that person's question is what seeds can
I plant in my mind to to be the buddhis
SATA to have the buddhis SATA reaction
to emptiness and not the physicist
reaction to emptiness you know what
separates a physicist from a bodh sappa
in this case there are lots of bodh
sappa physicists okay uh and I have to
say I and I believe it it's taking care
of normal people on a day-to-day basis
okay especially the elderly or the sick
okay or people who are have special
needs you know like
immigrants uh come to a new country
right Tana Arena and they don't know the
language and they don't know the
customs and then uh they need help uh if
I went to Ukraine and tried to live in
irin for
example that's where I would live by the
uh then I would need a Ukrainian person
to help me because I don't know I might
say the wrong thing I might do the wrong
thing you know so helping people who are
in new circumstances uh helping the
elderly gel and jig they're in a program
in around the capital of the universe
Rimrock and U they drive elderly people
to the grocery
store and they sit in the car for an
hour while the person decides what kind
of diapers they're going to buy you know
and uh and they do that like once a week
you know uh and things things like that
taking elderly people to the doctor is a
huge opportunity to plant the bodh saas
seeds uh so that when the moment comes
that you're close to seeing emptiness uh
The Bu SAA seats kick in and and you
have this experience of walking from
planet to planet there are almost all
high spiritual
goals come from the wild
reproduction of simple seeds almost high
spiritual goals come from the wild
reproduction of silly little seeds like
driving someone to the hospital or
taking them for their groceries and
stuff like that so that's a high buy
suffer practice and and it that's my
personal experience I had a personal
experience with that so I think uh it
worked for me and I and I spent many
many many days taking old people to the
hospital and doctor
and you
know Social Security Office it opens at
9: you have to get there by 6 and you
have to stand in line the line goes
around the buildings three four times on
the outside and it it's a snowstorm and
they will not let you in and you know
that kind of thing that's planting the
seeds to walk on different planets and
i' I've done that so many times and okay
all right all
right so another question here Gula
um
several people I'm combining questions
here several people have asked about
what is the difference between when we
talk about impermanence in general
things are impermanent and then having
an an awareness of subtle
impermanence oh yeah and what is a
subtle impermanence versus just general
normal
impermanence yeah okay good
um it's a favorite subject of mine and
I'll tell you a secret
okay
uh I
was I I got teachings on impermanence
and I wasn't satisfied with them and I
thought they didn't go deep enough uh so
I wrote a debate in
tibetan
uh to prove it wasn't deep enough you
know and uh and I wrote it out in
tibetan and I left it somewhere where a
certain llama would see
it and I didn't say
anything
and like the next day they're running
around the house like who wrote this
what is this you know where what book
did this come from you know and I'm like
I don't
know and
uh and it was cute anyway that's the
real story
uh and the Word impermanence was
bothering me uh for makaka or Ana in
Sanskrit so it's a
very it's a very central idea to
Buddhism as we saw yesterday if the
trees just blowing branches that don't
count it has to impart to you an
understanding of impermanence for examp
example okay the just wind blowing
through
trees is not necessarily Buddha sending
you a message there has to be a message
okay and uh it could
be if it's one of the four mudras which
is the four signs of a Buddhist teaching
is it should have teaching about
impermanence okay but there's a problem
with the English word impermanence and
we don't have a lot of time I'll give
give you a brief synopsis of my Tibetan
essay uh in America we have a thing
called a permanent resident card which
is a green card okay and
um and but nobody thinks it lasts
forever you see what I mean there's a
difference between forever and permanent
yeah I mean the green card expires when
you die okay like you can't can't pass
it on to the your children or something
like that uh it's a it's a permanent
resident card okay
so uh in English the word permanent I
mean it's un it's misused in that case
but permanent literally means it should
last forever okay that's permanent like
the sky is permanent or the universe is
permanent or something like that okay
then
impermanent in English means at some
point it will end okay so you know
actually a permanent resonant card is
impermanent okay if you think about it
okay so it will end at some time okay
but that's not what impermanence means
in Buddhism okay using the word
impermanence to
describe say
k k
okay something which goes in and out of
existence by the millisecond is the
definition of
impermanence it's not that it's gonna
wear out in six months or something like
that you know your new car Su
gang it's
impermanent okay you will discover
you'll be asking me gu who's the best
mechanic in Rim you know like they just
bought this beautiful new car which
means they're a real American now but uh
yeah one by one things will break and
you know Rob Ringer's new car broke the
first
day but what I'm saying is impermanent
means in English that sooner or later it
will start to break okay that's not what
it means in Buddhism in Buddhism it
means instantaneous
destruction second by second 65 times a
second
K
means uh dying and born second by second
okay die born die born die born die born
die born die born that's impermanence so
I don't like the word impermanence
impermanence means in English it stays
for a while and then it disappears but
in Buddhism it doesn't stay for a while
there's no such thing it it comes in and
goes out of existence Instant by instant
that's the definition of impermanence so
I don't like that I would rather say
changing changing Instant by instant I
think the word impermanence is
misleading and I feel that way about a
lot of translations But but so just
remember when we say impermanence in
Buddhism it doesn't mean you have to die
someday it means you are dying every
millisecond okay and the fact that you
live for a week is a is a
miracle okay okay got it all right so
that means there's no difference between
saying a impermanence and subtle
impermanence it's the same thing oh no
uh subtle impermanence is a different
thing okay subtle
impermanence depends on how deep you
want to go but thearer would say thearer
would say you ready yes going in and out
of existence Moment by moment
at what point did it change from going
into existence and going out of
existence Where's the
border between you know inexistence and
out of existence you know what's the
millisecond millisecond border between
the two and he'll say you cannot find it
you cannot find it okay
your census cannot perceive the length
of time it takes for all things to
change from starting to stopp it you you
do not have the sense capacity to detect
that your your senses do not have the
capacity uned by a microscope to detect
quarks or or atomic
particles msons your your senses don't
have the power okay so how do you see it
how how can it shift if the perception
is built of moments if the perception is
built of pieces of
perception then but you cannot see the
pieces how can you see the
whole it doesn't make sense okay it
doesn't make sense that you could
experience impermanence and that's
subtle impermanence
okay okay it it's not possible for you
to be perceiving subtle impermanence but
you do okay that's that's that's subtle
impermanence okay all right kids take a
break